Clifford Wight Collection relating to Diego Rivera
Clifford Wight Collection relating to Diego Rivera
1929-1941
Wight, Clifford.
1.25 linear ft.
Papers of the Mexican muralist. An epigrapher and sculptor, Wight acted as secretary, translator, and technical assistant to Diego Rivera during the latter's sojourn in the United States. Collection includes a variety of materials relating to Rivera's mural work in Detroit, San Francisco, and New York, including technical documents, correspondence, miscellaneous holograph and typescript manuscripts, photographs, and printed material.
149399
Biographical History
Diego Rivera (1886-1957) was a Mexican muralist. He studied in Mexico City and in Europe, and became a well-known for his cubist and post-Impressionist works. Rivera's works are in the permanent collections of museums across the United States and elsewhere, including the Art Institute of Chicago, the Fine Arts Museums of San Francisco, the Museum of Modern Art (New York City), the National Gallery of Art (Washington D.C.), Fundación Proa (Buenos Aires), the Hermitage Museum, Museo Nacional de Bellas Artes (Buenos Aires, Argentina), Museu de Arte de São Paulo (Brazil), and the Tehran Museum of Contemporary Art (Iran).
Clifford Wight (1900-ca. 1960), an Englishman, was a fellow artist and Rivera's secretary, translator and technical assistant during Rivera's work on murals in Detroit, New York and San Francisco. Rivera painted a portrait of Wight into one of the frescoes in the Secretariat of Education in Mexico City.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Clifford Wight Collection Relating to Diego Rivera comprises an assortment of materials which document the Mexican painter's mural work during his sojourn in the United States. An epigrapher and sculptor, Wight was approached via telegram from Rivera (24 Oct. 1931):
Please wire if you can go immediately to New York as my assistant to prepare walls for frescos. Your fare and twelve dollars [a] day for about six weeks ...
Wight acted as Rivera's secretary, translator and technical assistant through the completion of the murals in Detroit, New York and San Francisco. Spanning the years 1929 to 1941, the collection includes technical documents, correspondence, miscellaneous holograph and typescript manuscripts, photographs, printed material, and subject files.
The collection begins with a variety of Technical documents, the bulk of which is divided between two projects, the murals for the Detroit Institute of Arts (previously called the Detroit Museum of Art) and those for Rockefeller Center. Materials include agenda, cost analyses, proposals, specifications, and work schedules. Also among the technical documents are a chemical analysis of fresco application and a drawing of the panel layout for an unidentified mural.
Correspondence, generated between 1929 and 1933, is chronologically arranged and consists of both the incoming and outgoing letters of Diego Rivera and/or Clifford Wight. The correspondence is almost exclusively of a business nature and includes that with Clyde Burroughs and W.R. Valentiner of the Detroit Institute of Arts, the Cranbrook Academy of Art, Theodore Dreiser, Edsel Ford, William Gerstle, Albert Kahn, and Nelson Rockefeller. An index to the correspondence appears at the end of this inventory.
Following the correspondence is an assortment, arranged by author, of Miscellaneous manuscripts, both holograph and typescript. Included among these documents are George Biddle's "Plans for Study," which accompanies a blank fellowship application to the John Simon Guggenheim Foundation; two essays, Edgar P. Richardson's "The New World," and Diego Rivera's "The Position of the Artist in Russia Today"; a statement by Clifford Wight in defense of the Coit Tower murals; and the lyrics for a party song about Rivera by an unidentified author.
Photographs include images of Rivera's frescoes at the Detroit Institute of Arts, the Museum of Modern Art, the New Workers School, the San Francisco Art Insitute; several prints of what are believed to be examples of Clifford Wight's sculpture and epigraphy in stone; as well as three items labeled "fresco painting, Monterey, California" by an unidentified artist. Also among the photographs are several formal poses of Wight's wife, professional model Jean Abbott, and a number of candid shots of the couple's friends, including a few with Rivera and his wife, artist Frida Kahlo. In addition, the collection contains an assortment of photographs which appear to have been taken (by Wight?) in China during the early part of the 20th century.
Printed material comprises articles about Rivera's murals (1931 1939), newspaper clippings (1931 1941), and an assortment of ephemera. The articles are mainly selections from general interest periodicals (The American Mercury, The Commonweal, The Modern Monthly, The Nation, Time) while the clippings reflect coverage of the controversial artist by major American newspapers in Boston, Chicago, Detroit, Los Angeles, and New York as well as the British and Mexican press. Ephemera consists of a wide range of material, including advertisements, course catalogs, lecture announcements, and theatre programs.
The Subject file consists exclusively of visual material, and includes 3 original drawings by unidentified artists, general art references, and reproductions of Rivera's drawings and murals.
Arrangement of the Collection
Technical documents, manuscripts, photographs, and subject files are arranged alphabetically by title/topic. Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Printed material is subdivided by type and then arranged alphabetically by title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Abbott, Jean.; Abbott, Jere.; Burroughs, Clyde Huntley, 1882-; Dreiser, Thoedore, 1871-1945.; Ford, Edsel, 1893-1943.; Kahlo, Frida.; Kahn, Albert, 1869-1942.; Morris, Gouverneur, 1876-; Rivera, Diego, 1886-1957.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Valentiner, Wilhelm Reinhold, 1880-1958.; Wight, Clifford.; Cranbrook Academy of Art.; Detroit Institute of Arts.; Detroit Museum of Art.; Mexican American art.; Mural painting and decoration -- California.; Mural painting and decoration -- Michigan -- Detroit.; Mural painting and decoration --New York (State) -- New York.; Mural painting and decoration -- United States -- 20th century.; Painters, Mexico.; Public art.; Agendas (administrative records); Announcements.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Ephemera.; Manuscripts for publication.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Programs (documents); Specifications.; Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Technical documents
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, agenda, work schedules (Box 1)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, cost analyses (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller Center, proposal for subject matter of mural (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller Center, specifications (Box 1)
  - Chemical analysis of fresco process (Box 1)
  - Drawing of panel layout (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1929; 3 letters (Box 1)
  - [General], 1931; 5 letters, 3 telegrams (Box 1)
  - [General], 1932, Jan-Oct.; 9 letters (Box 1)
  - [General], 1932, Nov-Dec.; 10 letters, 2 enclosures, 1 draft (Box 1)
  - [General], 1933; 9 letters (Box 1)
  - [General], undated; 2 drafts (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous manuscripts
  - Biddle, George. "Plans for Study", 1931; statement attached to fellowship application to the John Simon Guggenheim Foundation (Box 1)
  - Richardson, Edgar P. "The New World", undated (Box 1)
  - Rivera, Diego. "The Position of the Artist in Russia Today", 1932 (Box 1)
  - Wight, Clifford, undated; statement in defense of Coit Tower murals (Box 1)
  - Unidentified author, lyrics "To the tune of Columbo", song about Rivera (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Diego Rivera frescoes
    - Detroit Institute of Arts, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Ministry of Education (Mexico City) (Box 1)
    - Museum of Modern Art (Oversize 1)
    - New Workers School (Box 1)
    - Rockefeller Center sketch (Box 1)
    - San Francisco Art Institute (Oversize 1)
    - Stern fresco (in progress) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Chapingo chapel doors after Rivera design (Box 1)
    - China (Box 1)
    - Clifford Wight, Jean Abbott, Kahlo, Rivera, and Mrs. Henry Ford (Box 1)
    - Clifford Wight with crew team (Oversize 1)
    - Clifford Wight's work (in question), 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Diego Rivera, Clifford Wight (Oversize 1)
    - Jean Abbott as professional model (Box 1)
    - Jean Abbott, Clifford Wight, and friends, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Jean Abbott, Frida Kahlo (Box 1)
    - Ralph Stackpole's work (Box 1)
    - Unidentified artist, "fresco painting, Monterey, California" (Oversize 1)
- Printed material
  - Articles
    - "Art and Rockefeller," The Nation, Apr. 4, 1934 (Box 1)
    - "Christ in a Skyscraper," Time, Sept. 25, 1933 (Box 1)
    - "Communist Riches," Time, Dec. 18, 1933 (Box 1)
    - "Concerning Senor Rivera," The Commonweal, May 26, 1933 (Box 1)
    - "Diego Rivera Mexican Master," Vanity Fair, June 1933 (Box 1)
    - "Diego Rivera the Artist of the People", undated (Box 1)
    - "The Diego Rivera Rockefeller Center and Detroit Museum of Art Murals," The Modern Monthly, undated (Box 1)
    - "The Famous Fresco by Diego Rivera," California Arts & Architecture, Dec. 1931 (Box 1)
    - "First photograph of the whole of Diego Rivera's mural in Rockefeller Center ..." The News Week at Home, June 3, 1933 (Box 1)
    - "Honor Among Revolutionaries," Time, Sept. 9, 1935 (Box 1)
    - "Michigan Miracle" / William Hard, undated (Box 1)
    - "New York Views the Rivera Controversy," D.A.C. News, undated (Box 1)
    - "Politics & the Painting of Business / Thomas Craven The American Mercury, Dec. 1932 (Box 1)
    - "Rivera in Reforma," Time, Nov. 30, 1939? (Box 1)
    - "Rivera's Murals ... Genius or Trash?" / George W. Stark D.A.C. News, Apr. 1933 (Box 1)
    - "Square Foot Show," Time, Dec. 28, 1931 (Box 1)
    - "What Is Art For?" / Diego Rivera The Modern Monthly, undated (Box 1)
    - "Zapata and White Horse", undated; full page reproduction of fresco, Museum of Modern Art, New York (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - Boston newspapers, originals, 1934 (Box 2)
    - Boston newspapers, copies (Box 2)
    - British newspapers, originals, 1935-1936 (Box 2)
    - British newspapers, copies (Box 2)
    - Chicago newspapers, originals, 1932-1933 (Box 2)
    - Chicago newspapers, copies (Box 2)
    - Detroit newspapers, originals, 1932-1933; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Detroit newspapers, copies (Box 2)
    - Los Angeles newspapers, originals, 1934 (Box 2)
    - Los Angeles newspapers, copies (Box 2)
    - Mexican newspapers, originals, 1933; 1935,; 1941 (Box 2)
    - Mexican newspapers, copies (Box 2)
    - The New York Times, originals, 1931-1933; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - The New York Times, copies, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - New York newspapers, originals, 1931-1933; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - New York newspapers, copies, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - San Francisco newspapers, originals, 1931 1937; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - San Francisco newspapers, copies, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous sources, originals, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous sources, copies, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Ephemera
    - "A. Ferrier's Theatre of Art La Gaite Francaise" January program (Box 2)
    - Advertisement, Jean Abbott, model (Box 2)
    - "Announcement of The American Spectator" (Box 2)
    - "The Art Workers' Guild ... 'Traditional and Modern Mural Painting'... Wight will show the scale drawings by Diego Rivera for Detroit" - lecture announcement, Mar 1937 (Box 2)
    - California School of Fine Arts, 1930-1931; 1931-1932; 2 catalogs, regular session; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - The Diego Rivera Frescoes: a Guide to the Murals of the Garden Court Detroit: People's Museum Association, circa 1933 (Box 2)
    - "The Diego Rivera Murals", pre-publication announcement of People's Museum Association pamphlet about murals (Box 2)
    - "La Gaite Francaise Theatre d'Art" season announcement, 1927-1928 (Box 2)
    - "The Museum of Modern Art announces a lecture on Diego Rivera" by Jere Abbott ..." lecture announcement (Box 2)
    - "Pacific Chinese Dramatic Club presents Mei Lan Fang ..." program (Box 2)
    - "Theatre d'Art" season announcement, 1930-1931 (Box 2)
- Subject files
  - Drawings, original, 3 by unidentified artists (Oversize 1)
  - References, general (Box 2)
  - References, oversize (Oversize 1)
  - Rivera murals, drawings, reproductions (Box 2)
  - Unidentified images (Box 2)
Index to correspondence
Abbott, Jere 27 Oct. 1931
Burroughs, Clyde H. see Detroit Institute of Arts Detroit Museum of Art
Butt, A. W. see Reinhard & Hofmeister, Corbett, Harrison & Mac Murray, Hood & Fouilhoux
Chase National Bank 16 Nov. 1932
Chicago Society of Artists 6 Feb. 1933
Cnossen, Sadie M. 14 Sept. 1932
Cranbrook Academy of Art 11 Nov. 1932 (2) 20 Jan. 1933 25 Jan. 1933
Detroit Institute of Arts 5 Feb. 1931 19 Nov. 1931 23 Nov. 1931 27 Nov. 1931 14 Dec. 1931
Detroit Museum of Art 17 May 1933
Detroit Tennis Club 18 May 1932
Ford, Edsel B. (secretary) 31 Oct. 1932
Gerstle, William Lewis 16 May 1929 24 May 1929 8 Oct. 1929 27 Jan. 1933
Kahn, Albert 5 Jan. 1932 27 July 1932 1 Nov. 1932
Lusk, George see Chicago Society of Artists
Morris, Gouverneur 10 Oct. 1933 28 Oct. 1933
Raseman, Richard P. see Cranbrook Academy of Art
Reinhard & Hofmeister, Corbett, Harrison & Mac Murray, Hood & Fouilhoux 13 Dec. 1932
Rivera, Diego 24 Oct. 1931 26 Oct. 1931
United States Gypsum Company 3 Jan. 1933
Valentiner, W. R. see Detroit Institute of Arts Detroit Museum of Art
Butt, A. W. See Reinhard & Hofmeister, Corbett, Harrison & Mac Murray, Hood & Fouilhoux
Cranbrook Academy of Art 20 Nov. 1932
Dreiser, Theodore 16 Dec. 1932 (2)
Ford, Edsel B. 22 Dec. 1932 (secretary) undated
Harrison, W. K. See Rockefeller, Nelson
The National Arts Club 21 Dec. 1932
Raseman, Richard P. see Cranbrook Academy of Art
Reinhard & Hofmeister, Corbett, Harrison & Mac Murray, Hood & Fouilhoux 18 Dec. 1932 12 Jan. 1933
Rockefeller, Nelson 20 Sept. 1932 (2) 10 Oct. 1932 18 Dec. 1932
Todd, Mr. (John R.?) 9 Oct. 1932